Preliminary Guide to the Carl V. Corley Papers, 1930s-1990s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carl V. Corley papers 1930s-1990s
Corley, Carl V.
24.0 linear feet Extent: 650 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
corley
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Purchased from Carl V. Corely in 1998.
Biographical Note
1921 Born in Florence, Mississippi
1939-1945 Served in the U.S. Marine Corps in the South Pacific
1947-1961 Illustrator, Staff Artist, and Unit Chief in the Mississippi Highway Department
1961-1981 Illustrator, Staff Artist, and Unit Chief in the Louisiana Highway Department
Carl V. Corley is an author and illustrator of a variety of materials such as gay "pulp fiction," comic books, physique art, science fiction, Louisiana history (especially on Cajun folkways), and also books on religious themes.
Corley was born in Florence, Mississippi in 1921. He graduated from Florence High School and served in the U.S. Marine Corps in the South Pacific in World War II. After the war, Corley worked as an illustrator for the Highway Department in Mississippi (1947-1961) and Louisiana (1961-1981). In his official capacities, he designed and drew tourist guides, manuals, pamphlets, road maps, and traffic surveys. In the 1970s and early 1980s, he contributed an illustrated strip on Louisiana folklore to the Eunice (LA) News.
In the 1950s, Corley made a name for himself as a "physique artist," as he contributed drawings of scantily clad men to fitness magazines--a genre that has been identified by cultural historians as early homoerotica. Between 1966 and 1971, he published twenty-two paper back novels of gay male "pulp fiction."
Collection Overview
The Carl V Corley Papers contains the writings, drawings, scrapbooks, notebooks, and published materials that document the career and artistic output of the novelist and illustrator. The collection includes copies of all twenty-two of Corley's published works of gay male pulp fiction. In addition to these published items, the collection also includes typescripsts and manuscripts of published and unpublished works of gay fiction, southern history, and heterosexual erotica, some of which is in the form of comic books or graphic novels. Corley's pulp novels were set primarily in early twentieth century Mississippi and Louisiana, though several were set in the South Pacific, where Corley served during World War II, and reflect varying degrees of autobiographical content. Corley's later works also show his interest in historical subject matter as well as utopian science fiction. Many of Corley's published and unpublished works include cover and textual illustrations produced byCorley. The collection further includes photographs of the artist and friends, works by related authors and artists, correspondence with publishers, and some work-related notes and materials.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Corley, Carl, 1921-; United States. Marine Corps -- History -- World War, 1939-1945; Marines -- United States; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- Sexuality -- Fiction; Gay men -- Comicbooks, strips, etc; Gay men -- Social life and customs -- Fiction; Homosexuality in art -- United States; Artists -- United States; Science fiction -- Illustrations; Authors, American -- 20th century; Illustrators -- United States; Authors and publishers -- United States -- Correspondence; Human figure in art; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Ocean; Cajuns -- Social life and customs; Cajuns -- History; Louisiana -- History; Mississippi -- History; Scrapbooks; Typescripts; Photographs
Separately Cataloged Material
A portion of printed materials written by Carl Carley and acquired with Acc. 1998-0087 have been separated from the manuscript collection and individually cataloged.
A Gay Trilogy, 1967
A Lover Mourned, 1967
Attala Rose, 1968
Cast a Wistful Eye, 1968
Faces in Secret, 1967
In Homage to Priapus, 1970, edited by E.V.Griffith (includes an excerpt from A Fool's Advice by Carl Corley)
Jesse, Man of the Streets, 1968
My Purple Winter, 1966
Sky Eyes, 1967
Swamp Angel, 1971
That Gay Bar, 1968(?), no author listed
The Scarlet Lantern, 1966
Cajun Casanovas, 1988
The Rafe Saxon Mystery, 1989
"Today and Tomorrow: an engineering analysis of the highway transportation system in Mississippi," 1949
"Louisiana Boys and Girls State," 1968
The Purple Ring
Contents of Collection
- Accession 1998-0087
  Scrapbooks, artwork, manuscripts and typescripts of published and unpublished works by Corley and books and and issues of magazines in which his work appears. Also included is correspondence relating to submission of work to publishers. Scrapbooks include photographs, drawings and notes relating to Corley's service in the Marine Corps in the Pacific during World War II. Scrapbooks also include research and preliminary studies for several books and comic strips. There are scrapbooks which document Corley's work for the Mississippi and Lousiana Departments of Highways. One scrapbook contains Corley's personal photographs of friends and lovers from high school to the present. Included are maps and posters relating to Mississippi and Lousiana history and geography created by Corley while working for the Department of Highways.
  - Correspondence, (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - Clippings (see also Oversize Boxes 1 and 15), (2 folders)
  - Scrapbooks: see also Oversize Boxes 1-2
    - Photograph album, 1930s-1990s
    - Clippinzgs about Pe'pa Paree
    - "Pe'pa Paree in the History of Eunice, Louisiana"
    - "Pe'pa Paree and the Story of Louisiana" (5 scrapbooks)
    - "Louisiana Festivals"
    - Work done for the Mississippi Highway Dept., 1947-1959 (3 scrapbooks)
    - "Papa Hi'wae Sez"
    - "Alex Cale, My First SF Comic Strip," 1939-1940
    - Floyd Raymond Comic Strip, 1938-1939
    - "Compiled Lexicon on Cowboy Lingo before writing Saddle Studs," (see Box 3) (Box 2)
    - "Preparation for Jambalee" (see Box 3)
  - Typescripts
    - The Martyr Heart
    - Tiga Polo Goes to Sola Roga
    - The Black Ruby
    - A New Earth
    - A Rose for Caesar
    - Jambalee
    - Jambalee (Box 3)
    - After a God
    - Soldiers in Silk: A Novel Based on Actual Experience
    - Heart of Anger
    - El Sabine
    - Rim of the World (with cover art)
    - Saddle Studs
    - Atomic Butterfly (Box 4)
    - Cad
    - Goddess in Amber
    - Ava
    - The Black Ruby
  - Manuscripts
    - Goddess in Genesis (with cover art)
    - Afro Mania (with cover art)
    - Gorgeous Light (with cover art)
    - Immortal Gods and Godless Mortals (with cover art)
    - Stardust
    - Star over Eden
    - Tara: A Sequel to Gone with the Wind (Box 5)
    - Jaffe Ben Jorden: A Robot who Played God
    - Alexander, the True Messiah
  - Illustrations and Cover Art (Box 6)
    Includes text for illustrated stories and comics, See also Oversize Boxes 13-16 and Oversize Cabinet IV:13.
    - Illustrated History of Genesis
    - Tee Don, Illustrated History of Acadiana
    - 20 Miniatures of Louisiana Folk Art
    - Kix
    - Fux, the Sex Fox
    - Blaze Star, Stellar Conqueror of Exotic Females
    - Sex Gods, an Exotic Pictorial (illustrated posters)
    - Rafe Saxon, Sex Warrior of Lust
    - Scenes from Jesus' Life (tempera painted tiles) (Box 7)
  - Oversize materials
    - Oversize Scrapbooks (Box OS1)
      - Clippings, Correspondence, Drawings, 1953-1983
      - "Album on Military Art, Marine Corps, World War II"
      - "World War II Scrapbook, 1940-1945" (Box OS2)
      - Genesis
    - Oversize Illustrations and Cover Art (Box OS3)
      - Illustrated History of Louisiana
      - Illustrated History of Louisiana (Box OS4)
      - Illustrated History of Louisiana (Box OS5)
      - Louisiana Folk Festivals (Box OS6)
      - Louisiana, Plantation Life, the Civil War and Reconstruction (Box OS7)
      - Louisiana, Plantation Life, the Civil War and Reconstruction (Box OS8)
      - Suny Blon (Box OS9)
      - Jafe Jule (Box OS10)
      - Jafe Ben Jordan (Box OS11)
      - Sola Flare
      - Roga (Box OS12)
      - Tiga Polo: Sex God of Stellar Space (Box OS13)
      - Miscellaneous Cover Art and Illustrations (Box OS14)
    - Oversize Clippings (Box OS15)
      - Corley's illustrations from the Eunice News
    - Oversize Posters and Maps designed by Corley
    - Oversize Illustrations (Box OS16)
      - Blaze Exotica
      - Sol Polo: Astral Calvalier (Box OS17)